I used to think
this was the beginning of your story.
Memory is a strange thing.
It doesn't work like I thought it did.
We are so bound by time,
by its order.
Okay.
Okay, come back to me.
Come back to me.
Stick 'em up!
Are you the sheriff in this here town?
These are my tickle guns,
and I'm gonna get ya.
No.
You want me to chase you?
You better run.
I remember moments in the middle.
I love you.
I hate you!
And this was the end.
Come back to me.
Baby, come back to me.
But now I'm not so sure
I believe in beginnings and endings.
There are days
that define your story beyond your life.
Like the day they arrived.
Good morning.
- Morning.
Where is everyone?
Okay. Well, let's get started.
Today, we are talking about Portuguese
and why it sounds so different
from the other Romance languages.
The story of Portuguese
begins in the kingdom of Galicia...
- Sorry.
- ...in the Middle Ages,
where language was seen
as an expression of art.
Any news you wanna share?
Dr. Banks, can you
turn the TV to a news channel?
...arrived here on scene,
but police have already set up
a blockade here around the area.
As you can see, we've gotten
just about as close as we can,
but unfortunately, Montana, right now,
is on complete lockdown.
The object apparently touched down
40 minutes ago just north of I-94.
We're waiting to hear if this is perhaps
an experimental vessel or...
Hold on.
I'm learning that
more objects like this have landed
at as many as eight other locations
around the world.
Yes. Can we?
This is from a site in Hokkaido.
This is worldwide.
It is happening right now.
Okay.
Guess class is dismissed.
Let's go. Keep moving.
For now,
we're simply asking for cooperation
while authorities assess the object.
So, you're saying it's not ours?
Do you even know if it's from Earth?
We're still collecting information.
We're coordinating with other countries.
We are not the only ones
to have one of these in our backyard.
If this is some sort of
peaceful first contact,
why send 12?
Why not just one?
Yeah, I know. I saw that, too.
I don't know, Mom. I'm watching
the same news coverage you are.
Well, Mom, please don't bother
with that channel.
How many times do I have to tell you
those people are idiots?
Yeah, well, do I sound nervous?
Okay, exactly. So...
Me? Yeah.
You know me, I'm about the same.
Mom, I'm fine.
Okay, I'll call you later. Bye.
And at around eight hours after landing,
there are still no signs
of what might be called "first contact."
Now, the objects measure
at least 1,500 feet tall.
Two are reported to have
penetrated Russian airspace,
one in Siberia and the other
off the coast of the Black
suspended above the ocean.
So far, there are 12 unidentified objects
spread across the globe.
There is no obvious logic
to their locations
and no evidence that the ships are even
who entertain the idea
that if it is a kind of vessel,
it may be unmanned.
Regardless, we have a protocol
for scenarios like this, but...
After Tuesday's extraordinary events,
the President, this morning,
has declared a state of emergency,
with as many as 5,000 National Guard
being deployed
to the state of Montana alone.
Borders are closed
and flights have been grounded,
stranding millions of travelers.
Panic buying of gas, water, and food
continues to escalate
and federal authorities
have temporarily lifted all caps
on overtime for law enforcement.
The ATF has put a temporary ban
on new gun licenses,
forcing many independent suppliers
of hunting equipment and firearms
to close their doors to the public.
Forty-eight hours later
and no further development...
Two days.
...from the sight of the 12 UFO...
And already the public expects us
to know the answers.
I'm Colonel G.T. Weber.
We never formally met,
but two years ago, you did some
Farsi translations for Army intelligence.
You made quick work
of those insurgent videos.
You made quick work of those insurgents.
You are on the top of everyone's list
when it comes to translations.
And you have another two years
in the SSBI.
So, you still have top-secret clearance.
That's why I'm in your office
and not at Berkeley.
Okay.
I have something
I need you to translate for me.
Why are you here?
Can you... Can you understand us?
Where did you come from?
Now you heard it.
What do you make of it?
Is that...
Yes.
How many?
How many what?
How many speaking?
Two.
Assume they were not speaking
at the same time.
Are you sure? Did they have mouths...
How would you approach translating this?
Do you hear any words?
Phrases?
I don't... I don't know.
So, what can you tell me?
I can tell you that it's impossible
to translate from an audio file.
I would need to be there
to interact with them.
You didn't need that
with the Farsi translations.
I didn't need it
because I already knew the language.
But this, this is...
I know what you're doing.
- Tell me what I'm doing.
- I'm not taking you to Montana.
It's all I can do to keep it
from turning into a tourist site
for everybody who has a TS clearance.
I'm just telling you
what it would take to do this job.
This is not a negotiation.
If I leave here, your chance is gone.
Good day.
Colonel?
You mentioned Berkeley,
are you going to ask Danvers next?
Maybe.
Before you commit to him,
ask him the Sanskrit word for "war"
and its translation.
An agreement on sharing scientific
discoveries looks closer tonight,
as Russia and China join talks
at the United Nations.
Meanwhile, financial markets
across the world are in crisis
as the Dow Jones Industrial Average
fell over 2,000 points
in its worst weekly decline in history.
Mornin'.
Colonel.
Gavisti. He says
it means "an argument."
What do you say it means?
"A desire for more cows."
Pack your bags.
All right, give me 20 minutes?
We take off in 10.
Dr. Banks. Right this way, please.
Contact and ready to approach...
Excuse me, Dr. Banks, let me
make sure you're properly secured.
You okay?
Thanks.
Sorry, I couldn't hear
what you were saying.
"Language is the foundation
of civilization."
"It is the glue
that holds a people together."
"It is the first weapon
drawn in a conflict."
Louise, this is Ian Donnelly.
Louise Banks, Ian Donnelly.
It's quite a greeting.
Yeah. Well, you wrote it.
Yeah, but...
It's the kind of thing you write
as a preface,
dazzle them with the basics.
Yeah. It's great.
Even if it's wrong.
It's wrong?
Well, the cornerstone of civilization
isn't language, it's science.
Ian is a theoretical physicist
from Los Alamos.
You'll be reporting to me,
but you'll be working with him
when you're in the shell.
That's what they're calling the UFO.
Priority one. What do they want,
where are they from.
And beyond that, how did they get here?
Are they capable of
faster-than-light travel?
Are they...
I have a list of questions that,
you know, we can go over.
Starting with a series of just
a "handshake" of binary sequences...
How about we just talk to them
before we start
throwing math problems at them?
This is why you're both here.
I'll bring the coffee.
Coffee with some aliens.
All right. I want you
to take these two to Dr. Kettler.
Yes, sir.
Follow the captain to Medical.
The procedure should take
just a few minutes,
and then, we'll get started.
These men are gonna
take care of your bags.
I'll take your cell phones.
Cell phones.
Follow me.
Put these on.
You're gonna wear them at all times.
- Not until they're here.
- Great.
Sir, they're here.
Louise Banks? Ian Donnelly?
When was the last time
either of you have eaten?
- Last night.
- Same.
When's the last time
you did something stressful?
Does now count?
Just saying.
Who was being carted off in the medevac?
Not everyone is able
to process experiences like this.
I'm gonna get some blood from you
and give you an immunization dose that
covers a battery of bacterial threats.
Would you sign these, please?
And roll up your sleeves.
Either of you claustrophobic?
- Nope.
- No.
Currently taking any medications?
Allergies? Pregnant?
No.
The booster is a kick to your system,
so you may experience some side-effects,
nausea, dizziness, headaches,
a ringing in your ears
like you have tinnitus.
You see what's happening to him?
How does this even work?
The readings do not change, but...
I don't know. It's like
we're insects on a piece of paper
and they're easing us out of the house.
At exactly 112 minutes and 19 seconds,
the gravity starts to shift
and slides us out of the room.
Have you found
a scientific explanation for it?
Like, is it for them?
No, we think it's for us.
The air doesn't seem to circulate
inside the chamber,
so after about two hours,
you run out of oxygen.
It doesn't take 18 hours
to pump fresh air into a room.
Atmosphere.
Excuse me?
If their atmosphere
is different from Earth,
it would certainly take hours
to rebalance the O2 content
and pressure for us
every time they open their door.
So, you're saying they could
suffocate us if they wanted?
This is Agent David Halpern with the CIA.
Let me get you two to your stations.
Yes, sir.
Remember, we need answers
as soon as possible.
What do they want,
where are they from, why they're here.
- This is the priority.
- Yeah.
Everyone, this is Dr. Ian Donnelly.
He'll be running this team here.
Yeah, have they responded to anything?
Shapes, patterns, numbers, Fibonacci?
We can't tell what they are saying
when they respond to "hello,"
so don't get ahead of yourself.
What have you figured out?
We're just getting started.
- Good morning.
This is Dr. Louise Banks.
She'll be heading your team.
- Dr. Banks. It's a pleasure meeting you.
- Hi.
Dr. Banks is taking over
the mission from Dr. Walker.
- Nice to see you.
- Dr. Banks, glad to see you.
That's your 15-minute warning.
You scuba-dive before?
What kind of radiation exposure
are we walking into?
Nominal, these are just for safety.
So, is there any physical contact
with the...
Am I the only one having
trouble saying "aliens"?
There's a wall, like a glass wall.
You can't get to them.
So, what do they look like?
You'll see soon enough. Hurry up.
Thank you. Turn this way, please.
All units, stand by. Over.
The suits are clumsy at first,
but you get used to them.
Load up in the second vehicle.
Hurry up, hurry up. Bring it over here.
We're clear over here, sir.
All set, sir. This is the last box
for this truck. This truck's clear.
Let's go!
We'll be there in a few minutes.
Make sure you hold on to something.
We are now inside the demilitarized zone.
- Raise 1.2 klicks. Over.
- Copy, Alpha.
We'll continue to monitor vitals
and signal clarity from operations.
Air picket's in position
and fully operational.
Countermeasures in place
and ready for deployment. Over.
Copy, Condor.
We will observe, but not initiate. Over.
Watch your step.
We'll keep Alpha channel open. Over.
Alpha, be advised.
Humidity increased since yesterday.
Every 18 hours,
the door opens up at the bottom.
That's where we go in.
Red team on standby.
Zero movement.
Alpha detail, clear to proceed. Over.
Copy, Condor.
Beginning our ascent now. Over.
Ten feet.
Five feet.
Two. One.
Alpha, clear
to enter antechamber. Over.
Copy, Condor.
Moving into position. Over.
Thirty feet from target.
Suit telemetry now full strength,
despite unknown interference. Over.
Five feet. Two, one.
Oxygen level, 20.3%.
No known contaminates. Over.
Vitals normal.
Gravity at 0.97.
Radio signal strength decreasing.
90%. 85%. Fluctuating...
Yeah, that just happened.
All right, let's move. Time is wasting.
You ready?
Let's do it.
Condor, I'm proceeding first
with Captain Marks. Over.
Radio signal strength 75%. Over.
Landed. Gravity nominal
in the antechamber. Over.
It's all good, sir.
- You can proceed.
- Stand by.
Okay, bring it up.
Vitals in line.
Radio signal strength
stable at 75%. Over.
You okay?
Yeah.
Dr. Banks.
You can do this.
Come on.
I don't know, I... I think...
Grab her.
Dr. Donnelly, are you all right?
Dr. Donnelly. You good?
Please respond. Over.
Yeah.
Holy fuck.
We're gonna go down there,
and you're gonna start your job.
Okay.
- Okay? Everybody, move out.
- Okay.
Alpha detail is in position.
Team is in position.
We're on the move.
Condor, Alpha's now in the nave.
Setting up equipment
and telemetry. Over.
Oxygen level, 21.3%. Over.
So, what happens now?
They arrive.
Dr. Banks.
You can start.
Alpha detail, proceed directly
through the decontamination
to the inner airlock.
Do not stop until you have passed
through the airlock doors.
Do not attempt to remove the hazmat suit
without proper assistance
of authorized personnel.
Repeat. Hazmat suits without
assistance of authorized personnel.
- Wait, just a minute. A minute.
- All right.
Keep your head low.
Clear.
- All right.
- Step on out, please.
Now hold that.
Am I fired?
You did better than the last guy.
That doesn't make me feel any better.
You both have till 0200 hours
to figure something out.
Okay, what happens then?
You go back in.
Violence continues
to spread across the US today
in the wake of the 12 landings.
The President has declared
a mandatory dusk-to-dawn curfew
after the crackdown by the National Guard
failed to prevent a third night
of looting across the country.
In North Dakota, 144 members
of the St. Lawrence Pentecostal Cult
are feared dead
after they set their compound ablaze.
Their website claims
the arrival of the aliens
set in motion a prophecy that
12 sets of 12 should "follow the lamb."
And this is Seven-November.
Roger, stand by...
Got that request...
We're up in 15. You got any new intel?
Yeah, we've been playing back
some of their sounds.
Where does that get you?
Well, they play audio back at us
from an unseen source.
Audio of what?
It's bits of conversation from the room,
random clips of dialogue.
Really, we... We have nothing.
T-minus 14 minutes to shell access.
Are you receiving my signal?
Yes. It's sending.
- Okay, thanks.
- Okay. Good hunting.
Heading out.
Checking in for radio.
Are you receiving me?
You're coming in loud and clear.
Good luck, Doctor.
T-minus nine minutes to shell access.
What's that for?
A visual aid.
Look, I'm never going to be able to
speak their words if they are talking.
But they might have
some sort of written language
or basis for visual communication.
Okay. Let's get started.
Human.
"Human."
I'm human.
What are you?
Human.
Affirmative, Alpha...
Oh, my God.
Are you getting this?
Yes, sir.
It's uploading back to base camp.
Louise.
That's incredible.
Human.
Okay.
Okay, slow down, fellas.
Slow down.
I don't wanna take away
from your success in there,
but, Dr. Banks,
is this really the right approach?
Trying to teach 'em
how to speak and read?
That's gotta take longer.
You're wrong. It's faster.
Everything you do in there
I have to explain to a room full of men
whose first and last question is,
"How can this be used against us?"
So, you're gonna
have to give me more than that.
Kangaroo.
What is that?
In 1770,
Captain James Cook's ship ran
aground off the coast of Australia,
and he led a party into the country
and they met the Aboriginal people.
One of the sailors pointed
at the animals that hop around
and put their babies in their pouch,
and he asked what they were,
and the Aborigines said, "Kanguru."
And the point is?
It wasn't until later that they learned
that "kanguru" means "I don't understand."
So, I need this so that we
don't misinterpret things in there,
otherwise this is
gonna take 10 times as long.
I could sell that for now.
But I need you
to submit your vocabulary words
before the next session.
Fair.
And remember
what happened to the Aborigines.
A more advanced race
nearly wiped 'em out.
It's a good story.
Thanks.
It's not true.
But it proves my point.
We think we were able to reproduce
some prime number sequences back at them.
So, that's something.
Well, congratulations. You're a parrot.
Well, it's a lot more than that,
you cheeky bastard.
Don't you see?
They can't seem to follow our algebra.
But complex behaviors? That clicks.
Well, that doesn't make
any sense at all, does it?
The problem is, not everyone shares
our policy of being open with the aliens.
Have you met General Shang?
Call sign for him is "Big Domino."
Whatever Shang does,
at least four other nations will follow.
- Louise, you have to gain ground today.
- Okay.
- You have a vocabulary list for me?
- I do.
You're gonna teach them
your name and Ian's?
Yes, so that we can learn their names,
if they have names,
and then introduce pronouns later.
These are all grade-school words.
"Eat." "Walk."
Help me understand.
Okay.
No, no, no, not the top!
Okay, this is
where you wanna get to, right?
- That is the question.
- Okay.
So, first we need to make sure
that they understand what a question is.
Okay? The nature
of a request for information
along with a response.
Then, we need to clarify
the difference between
a specific "you" and a collective "you,"
because we don't want to know
why Joe Alien is here.
We want to know why they all landed.
And "purpose" requires
an understanding of intent.
We need to find out,
do they make conscious choices
or is their motivation so instinctive
that they don't understand
a "why" question at all.
And... And biggest of all, we need to
have enough vocabulary with them
that we understand their answer.
I get it.
Stick to your list.
Just don't add anything to it.
Gravity, 0.97.
Oxygen level, 21.4%. Over.
Condor, Alpha's now in the main.
Setting up equipment
and telemetry. Over.
Let's get started.
"Louise."
Louise. I am Louise.
What is that?
Is that a new symbol? I can't tell.
I don't know.
I think it's the symbol for "human" again.
It just has a little curl on the end,
maybe to indicate a question.
I don't know.
I don't know, Louise.
I think they're getting confused.
Dr. Banks, perhaps we should
move on to the next word.
Dr. Banks?
- It's okay, Nate.
- What's going on?
Hey, hey, hey. What are you doing?
- Yeah, I'm fine.
- Are you insane?
They need to see me.
She's taking off her hazmat suit.
Dr. Banks!
Is it okay?
You're risking contamination.
They need to see me.
Dr. Banks.
She's walking towards the screen.
Should we abort?
Request noted. Stand by for frag order.
Go back to your stations.
Now that's a proper introduction.
Okay.
"Louise."
I am Louise.
Ian, you want to introduce yourself?
Yeah.
Louise.
Screw it.
Everybody dies, right?
Sir, Donnelly is taking off
his hazmat suit.
Permission to abort?
Continue the session.
Ian.
Louise.
You.
Who are you?
I think those are their names.
They have names.
So, what are we gonna call them?
I don't know.
I was thinking Abbott and Costello.
Yeah.
- Yeah?
- Yeah, I like it.
I like it.
Team 1, exit your vehicle
and proceed directly ahead
to the decontamination tent.
Leave your respirator on
until you reach the equipment room.
I know.
Team 2, exit your vehicles and continue
to the decontamination tent.
Leave your respirators on
and do not hesitate
until you reach the equipment room.
How do you feel?
Overworked.
Well, I guess I don't need to tell you,
you're putting yourself at risk.
There are no signs
of radiation poisoning yet.
We'll see how your blood tests look.
For now, I'm gonna
give you another boost.
Okay.
No radiation.
Nothing else we can detect either,
but I'd give 'em
a strong cocktail regardless.
It's the first time
we've made significant progress.
All right.
We'll take the risk.
- Okay, honey...
- What is going on there?
- Honey.
- Ls there anything you can tell me?
No... You don't need to worry, okay?
- How can I not worry?
- Just calm down.
Just calm down.
Becky asked me if the monsters
are going to kill Daddy.
Honey, it's not gonna happen.
Just stay safe.
You don't need to worry.
Please, I'm so scared.
All junior xenolinguistics
and science personnel must observe
general curfew
unless expressly authorized
for extended work hours by unit COs.
Curfew in effect as of 2200 hours.
Notice to all late workers,
fire watchers and night staff.
Effective immediately, midnight rations
will be served all night.
Here are some of the many things
we don't know about heptapods.
Greek. Hepta, "Seven. "Pod, "Foot."
"Seven feet." Heptapod.
Who are they?
Trying to answer this
in any meaningful way
is hampered by the fact that,
outside being able
to see them and hear them,
the heptapods leave
absolutely no footprint.
The chemical composition
of their spaceship is unknown.
The shell emits no waste,
no gas, no radiation.
Assuming that the shells
communicate with each other,
they do so without detection.
The air between the shells is untroubled
by sonic emission or light wave.
Are they scientists or tourists?
If they're scientists, they don't seem
to ask a lot of questions.
Why did they park where they did?
The world's most decorated experts
can't crack that one.
The most plausible theory is that
they chose places on Earth
with the lowest incidence
of lightning strikes.
But there are exceptions.
The next most plausible theory is that
Sheena Easton had a hit song
at each of these sites in 1980.
So, we just don't know.
How do they communicate?
Here, Louise is putting us all to shame.
The first breakthrough was to discover
that there's no correlation
between what a heptapod says
and what a heptapod writes.
Unlike all written human languages,
their writing is semasiographic.
It conveys meaning.
It doesn't represent sound.
Perhaps they view our form of writing
as a wasted opportunity,
passing up a second
communications channel.
We have our friends in Pakistan
to thank for their study
of how heptapods write.
Because, unlike speech,
a logogram is free of time.
Like their ship or their bodies,
their written language has
no forward or backward direction.
Linguists call this
"nonlinear orthography,"
which raises the question,
"Is this how they think?"
Imagine you wanted to
write a sentence using two hands,
starting from either side.
You would have to know
each word you wanted to use
as well as
how much space that it would occupy.
A heptapod can write a complex sentence
in two seconds, effortlessly.
It's taken us a month to make
the simplest reply.
Next, expanding vocabulary.
Louise thinks it could easily take
another month to be ready for that.
Hey.
Weber's looking for you.
Yeah, well, why do you think
I'm hiding out here?
Come on up.
Come on.
Thanks.
Nice out here, huh?
Yeah, it's a nice view.
Away from the noise.
You know, I was just thinking about you.
You approach language
like a mathematician.
You know that, right?
I will take that as a compliment.
Yeah, well, it is.
It's...
I watch you steer us around
these communication traps
that I didn't even know existed.
Say what?
I guess that's why I'm single.
Trust me, you can
understand communication
and still end up single.
I feel like
everything that happens in there
comes down to the two of us.
Yeah, it's a good thing though, right?
You and I?
Have you seen the jokers
that we're working with?
I'm glad I got you.
Tonight, the first photograph
of the aliens goes viral.
Biological contamination is
a major risk factor at the Montana site,
so say environmental pressure groups.
Eight-hundred thousand
march on Washington
to protest
the government's handling of the crisis.
All this, and more special coverage.
First contact with whoever it is
that is inside that thing,
and who do we have running the show?
The government.
That's right, folks.
The same government
who ruined our healthcare
and bankrupted our military.
Look at these people.
Most of them don't even have guns.
We could be facing a full-scale invasion,
and our president
is just willing to sit back
and let them waltz in
and take our country.
We are falling asleep
at the wheel, people.
You know what I'm talking about.
I know you do.
What if the smartest thing
we could do right now
would be to give them a show of force?
I'm talking about a shot across the bow.
I wanna hear what you think.
Caller number one, you're on the air.
What do you think about all this?
What's this word?
"Planet."
No, no.
That's, like... The Earth is a planet.
Want to see my project
from Miss Garriott's class?
Yeah, little nose.
We had to make up our own TV show.
If we had one.
- And who are those two people?
- That's you and Dad.
The show is called
Mommy and Daddy Talk to Animals.
Well, it's lovely.
Okay.
You know it's okay to be sad
that your dad and I...
I know. I'm not.
'Cause we both love you very much.
I know. It's just a cartoon. Not real.
Louise?
You all right?
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm fine.
I'm not sure it's something I can explain.
When was your last checkup
with Dr. Kettler?
I'm okay.
I'm gonna get some air.
- All right.
- I'm fine. Yeah.
How you feeling?
I need some sleep, but I'm fine.
Yeah.
You know, I was doing some reading
about this idea that
if you immerse yourself
into a foreign language,
that you can actually rewire your brain.
Yeah, the Sapir-Whorf Hypothesis.
The theory that...
It's the theory that
the language you speak
determines how you think and...
Yeah. It affects how you see everything.
It was...
I'm curious,
are you dreaming in their language?
I may have had a few dreams,
but I don't...
I don't think that
that makes me unfit to do this job.
Did you sleep?
A little.
Do you know Mandarin?
It is shifting.
The voice you're about to hear
belongs to China's military chief,
General Shang.
Pull it up.
We got a satellite feed here
of who he's talking to,
if you want to look.
Wait, go back.
Stop.
He's saying that each of the 12
is offering advanced technology.
And back again. And play.
"Our science team is attempting
to decode the sets."
"Sets." I don't know what that means.
Something about advantage.
"Suits, honor, and flowers."
I don't...
I don't know, that's all.
I don't know what it means either.
An hour ago, China mobilized forces.
And now, Russia is following suit.
Shang's about to start something.
Following suit, "suits."
Suits. Honor. Flowers.
Colonel, those are all
tile sets in mahjong.
God, are they...
Are they using a game
to converse with their heptapods?
Maybe. Why?
Well, let's say that I taught them chess
instead of English.
Every conversation would be a game,
every idea expressed
through opposition, victory, defeat.
You see the problem?
If all I ever gave you was a hammer...
Everything's a nail.
We need to ask the big question.
Ready or not.
Right, so...
Okay, let me know
what temperature you use, okay?
No, this is the same as before.
- See.
- I...
Yeah, no, but between three and four.
- All right, time to go.
- Okay.
Ninety-six minutes remaining
in the session. Over.
Okay.
Heptapod's purpose.
Heptapod purpose. Earth.
What is your purpose?
Do we only have Costello?
Okay. There you are.
What does it say?
"Offer weapon."
But you saw what they wrote.
Using a word they don't fully understand.
- It could be just a request.
- Or a warning.
Enough!
Louise?
We don't know if they understand
the difference between
a weapon and a tool.
Our language, like our culture, is messy,
and sometimes one can be both.
I think it's quite possible that they're
asking us to offer them something,
not the other way around,
like the first part of a trade.
So, how do we clarify their intentions
beyond those two words?
Well, I go back in.
Right away, we go back in
and we clear this up.
It's more complicated than that.
How is it more complicated than that?
Colonel, the Secretary of Defense
is on the line for you.
We need to sit on this information
till we know what it means.
So, we aren't sharing it
with our enemies.
We have to consider the idea
that our visitors are prodding us
to fight among ourselves
until only one faction prevails.
There's no evidence of that.
Sure there is.
Just grab a history book.
The British with India,
the Germans with Rwanda.
They even got a name for it in Hungary.
Yeah.
We're a world with no single leader.
It's impossible to deal with
just one of us.
And with the word "weapon" now...
Halpern.
Yes, sir.
Copy that. Waiting for instructions.
No confirmation yet.
Standing by.
Anything?
What did they say?
China and Russia are off the grid.
They aren't speaking to anyone.
Whatever they learned
in their last session has them spooked.
Yes, sir.
We have orders to do the same.
Wait, these are our allies.
Colonel, you can't shut us down.
- Put us on radio silence.
- Do it.
We received a message from the...
Damn it!
We need to be talking to each other.
You wanna talk to them?
Find out what this means.
Base-camp talk is now offline.
- All interpreters...
- No confirmation. They're offline.
...stand down
and report to unit coordinators.
We've never re-entered a session before.
Look, Louise, trust me, okay?
We've got time.
We've just gotta step on it, all right?
"Use weapon."
This is the alien message
said to have provoked
the Chinese government
to withdraw their scientists
from the international mission today.
In a statement, General Shang said,
"China no longer trusts the aliens
who want to divide us."
"Humanity must be protected."
China has asked for immediate talks
at the UN.
Alpha one-niner, this is Condor. Over.
Alpha one-niner, this is Condor.
Come in. Over.
Captain Marks, Condor.
Not receiving transmission.
Squelch twice if you hear mine.
Captain Marks, all escort groups
are ordered to cease all activity.
No, no, no.
Dr. Banks, you can't go in there.
We just need to ask one question.
Dr. Banks, the session is finished.
You can't...
You can't go back in. It's dangerous.
Look, we just need five minutes.
Don't sweat it.
Marks, let them go.
Hey, Abbott.
So, what are we calling this, session 37?
No, 36, part two.
Okay.
Yeah.
Why are they on their own?
We've been attempting
to hail Captain Marks.
The escort units are not responding, sir.
Why not?
Send security.
"Offer weapon. Question mark."
Are you offering us something?
"Technology. Apparatus. Method"?
Yeah, see, this is a different word.
This segment, it's a lot busier.
"Give."
"Technology."
"Now."
What's he doing?
Captain, on your 10.
Mutineers are to be apprehended
without engaging.
We don't want to risk
antagonizing our visitors. Over.
Security detail inbound, sir.
T-minus four minutes remaining.
We need to see this through.
Okay, this is it. Lock and load.
We just need to hold them off
until it's done.
Copy that.
Warning shots as explicit fire only.
Load up and get to cover.
Stay fresh and we can avoid casualties.
Abbott wants me to write on the barrier.
Can you even do that?
I don't know.
I can't do it with both hands.
Louise.
What is that?
- Free fire!
- Over there! I'm hit! I'm hit!
Hey, hey, hey. Take it easy.
You suffered a concussion.
Just lay back.
How are you feeling?
How is Ian?
Same as you. He's okay.
Who...
Who did this?
Some soldiers.
Been watching too much TV.
What is that?
Now, take it easy. Take it easy.
The site's no longer secure.
We're standing by to evacuate.
Where's Ian?
Weber came and got him
maybe 10 minutes ago.
But he wouldn't leave
until he knew you were okay.
The whole tent is on the clock
to figure out whatever it is
you were given up there.
This is all of it.
The feed wasn't interrupted
by the explosion?
Not as far as we can see.
You see something?
I don't know yet.
I'm gonna need my team
to get together with Louise's team.
I need everybody working on this.
We cannot leave.
Glad to see you're awake.
We need to go back in and we need
to explain to them this wasn't our fault.
- We can't go back inside.
- We have to tell them... We have to.
What happened in there was an attack.
We can hope for the best, but
I have orders to prepare for retaliation.
We may have to evacuate.
No, that's the wrong move.
As long as they stay, we have to stay.
Well, they're not leaving.
Why does this feel worse?
China is on the offensive.
They're positioning their military
to blow the alien vessel
right out of the sky.
And if this happens,
we can't sit around waiting
for retaliation, so get prepared.
The Air Force and infantry
are standing by.
Yes, sir.
Tonight, China becomes
the first world power
to declare war against the aliens.
Following the failure of
diplomatic efforts at the United Nations,
China has confirmed that
its language experts have, tonight,
delivered an ultimatum
at the Shanghai site.
In a televised statement, General Shang,
Chairman of the People's Liberation Army,
said the aliens have 24 hours
to leave Chinese territory
or face destruction.
And he urged all other world leaders
to unite with China
and take a similar stance.
With a huge buildup of forces
at their landing sites,
Pakistan, Russia, and Sudan are
thought to be following China's lead.
It can't be random.
It's going to take us years.
What's this term here?
Mom.
Sweetie?
What's this term for that thing like a...
Like a technical term?
Where we make a deal and
we both get something out of it?
"Compromise."
No.
Like, it's a competition,
but both sides end up happy.
Like a win-win.
More science-y than that.
If you want science, call your father.
Thank you.
Sorry.
It's okay. I'm up.
What time is it?
It's time you open that bottle
you've been hiding.
You cracked something, didn't you?
Yeah, come here.
Take a look at this section.
It seems to be talking about time.
Their symbol for "time" is everywhere.
So, what is this?
A formula for faster-than-light travel?
Who can tell?
There are too many gaps.
Nothing's complete.
Then it dawned on me.
Come here.
Right here.
Stop focusing on the ones,
look at the zeroes.
How much of this is data?
How much of it is negative space?
So, I measured it.
0.0833 recurring.
Perhaps you'd like that as a fraction.
One of 12.
What they're saying right here
is that this is one of 12.
We are part of a larger whole.
Or we're one of 12 contestants
for the prize.
Why do I have to talk to him?
We're all working together here.
We need to talk to the other sites.
We need to help them with what they've
gotten from the other heptapods.
In case you don't remember,
we're blacked out.
China just threatened to destroy
their shell. We're on our own.
Yeah, but this says that
all of the pieces fit together.
And I'm telling you
that no one else cares.
Two hours ago, we pulled this audio
off a secure channel in Russia.
Someone on the science team there
was broadcasting wide.
In their final session, the alien said,
"There is no time."
"Many become one."
I feel we have all been given weapons.
If anyone is receiving this, please...
Well, I mean,
there are a lot of ways
you can interpret what he's saying.
I don't need an interpreter
to know what this means.
Russia just executed
one of their own experts
to keep their secrets.
"Many become one" could
just be their way of saying,
"Some assembly required."
Why hand it out to us in pieces?
Why not just give it all over?
Well, what better way to force us
to work together for once?
Even if I did believe you,
how in the world you gonna get
anybody else to play along
or give up their data?
We offer ours in return.
Yeah?
What, trade?
It's a non-zero sum game.
"Non-zero sum game."
That's it.
Yeah, thanks.
Nine of the landing sites
have gone total comms blackout.
Only way to reach them
is to physically drive there and yell
at the border guards, which we're doing,
but it won't be fast enough.
There's got to be a way to...
To get the message to them.
To our allies maybe, but at this stage,
it's too little too late.
What we need is to get
all the other nations online
before one starts global war,
and there's no way for us to reach them.
Wait. Hold on a second.
There is.
It's right above us.
That's problematic for us right now.
The Pentagon's convinced
our shell will retaliate.
My guess is they'll order us
to evacuate within the hour.
Look, they're not our enemy.
They've made
no act of aggression towards us.
Maybe this is
their way of being aggressive.
That's not the question.
Well, what is the question?
How do we get you back in that room
when it's half a mile straight up?
I think our work here is done.
It's in the hands of our superiors now.
What the hell is she doing?
No. God. Oh, God. No.
Costello?
Where's Abbott?
Abbott is death process
I'm sorry.
We're sorry.
I need you to...
I need you to send a message
to the other sites.
Louise has weapon
Use weapon
I don't...
I don't understand.
What is your purpose here?
We help humanity
In three thousand years
we need humanity help
How can you know the future?
I don't...
I don't understand.
Who is this child?
The show is called
Mommy and Daddy Talk to Animals.
Louise sees future
Weapon opens time
Wait.
No... Wait!
- Dr. Banks!
- Louise!
Are you all right?
- Hey. You all right?
- Yeah.
- Here, come on. What happened?
- I'm fine.
Tried to figure it out. This is too big.
Doesn't matter now.
We have orders to evacuate.
- Why?
- Russia and Sudan are following China.
Ian. I don't understand why the...
Help me, Mama.
Louise?
Oh, my God.
Mom.
Mama!
Sorry, honey.
What day is it? Do you know, baby?
Sunday.
Are you gonna leave me like Daddy did?
Hannah, honey,
your daddy didn't leave you.
You're gonna see him this weekend.
He doesn't look at me
the same way anymore.
That's my fault.
I told him something
that he wasn't ready to hear.
What?
Well, believe it or not,
I know something that's going to happen.
I can't explain how I know. I just do.
And when I told your daddy,
he got really mad.
And he said I made the wrong choice.
What? What's going to happen?
It has to do with a really rare disease.
And it's unstoppable.
Kind of like you are.
Your swimming, and your poetry,
and all the other amazing things
that you share with the world.
I am unstoppable?
Yeah.
I got you.
Louise?
Louise.
I just realized why my husband left me.
My husband left me.
You were married?
Come on. Let's get out of here.
Mama?
Yeah?
Why is my name Hannah?
Yeah, got it right here.
Get those people back, please.
Well, your name is very special
because it is a palindrome.
It reads the same forward and backward.
- All right, guys, give me a hand here.
- Yes, sir.
That goes in the back.
Civilian contractors must have their
authorization badges
and passkeys when checking...
Evacuation underway...
Hey.
Look, we're done here.
We're taking this with us.
I can read it.
- I know what it is.
- What?
It's not a weapon, it's a gift.
The weapon is their language.
They gave it all to us.
Do you understand what that means?
So we can learn Heptapod, if we survive.
If you learn it, when you really learn it,
you begin to perceive time
the way that they do.
So you can see what's to come.
But time, it isn't the same for them.
- It's non-linear.
- Look.
We did our best, but it wasn't enough.
The captain will load you up.
You're lifting off in five minutes.
Ian, Louise,
it was an honor to work with ya.
Good luck.
Hey, Colonel!
I'm gonna find out where we're going.
Wake up, Mommy.
Dr. Banks.
A pleasure.
General Shang.
The pleasure is mine, really.
Your President said
he was honored to host me
at the celebration...
- Yes.
- ...but I confess,
the only reason why I'm here is to
meet you in person.
Me? Well, I'm flattered. Thank you.
Now, 18 months ago,
you did something remarkable.
Something not even my superior has done.
And what's that?
You changed my mind.
You're the reason for this unification.
All because you reached out to me
on my private number.
Your private number.
General, I don't know
your private number.
Now you know.
I do not claim to know
how your mind works,
but I believe it was important for you
to see that.
I called you, didn't I?
Yes, you did.
Louise.
- All right, let's shut down the system.
- Sir.
There's a sat-line here dialing China.
Here? What do you mean "here"?
Come on, come on.
Whose phone is it?
It's your phone, sir.
Search base camp now.
Find out who's using that phone.
- Hold on to those coordinates.
- Yes, sir.
Come on. What'd I say?
What'd I say? Come on.
Come on.
I will never forget what you said.
You told me my wife's dying words.
Found the source of the phone call.
It's in the clean room.
Waiting for instructions.
What are you doing?
- What are you doing?
- Changing someone's mind.
- Can you buy me 20 seconds?
- We don't have time for this right now.
No, trust me, buy me 20 seconds.
Do you trust me?
- Okay! Yeah.
- You trust me?
Dr. Banks!
Drop the phone now or we shoot!
- Drop it!
- Yeah. I'm sorry!
You're committing an act of treason!
- Yes.
- Drop it!
It's done. I'm done.
Communications blackout from all 12
landing sites continues this evening.
Hold on, we are just hearing...
And I'm being told
we're going to cut this report
to tell you breaking news.
Breaking now, China has called
an emergency press conference.
General Shang, Commander-in-chief
of the People's Liberation Army,
has announced in
an emergency press conference
that China is standing down.
China is stating that
all intelligence they have received
will be shared immediately
with all the other landing sites.
Scientists from around the world
are sifting through information received
- from the UK, Japan...
- Breaking news,
the Russian armed forces are now
revealing the information
they've acquired from
both of their landing sites
and have declared the Black Sea
a demilitarized zone.
...one of the 12 pieces of this puzzle
that's being slowly put together.
So, Hannah.
This is where your story begins.
The day they departed.
You all right?
Despite knowing the journey
and where it leads...
I embrace it...
and I welcome every moment of it.
- H-A-N-N-A-H.
- Now backward. H-A-N-N-A-H.
- A-N-N-A-H.
Hannah.
You ready, baby?
Okay.
Hi.
- You good?
- All right. See ya.
Daddy!
You okay?
Daddy's gonna roll over you.
All right, you ready?
Guess what? Star stuff.
- Ian...
- Yeah?
If you could see your whole life
from the start to finish...
would you change things?
Maybe I'd say what I feel more often.
I... I don't know.
You know, I've had my head tilted up to
the stars for as long as I can remember.
You know what surprised me the most?
It wasn't meeting them.
It was meeting you.
I forgot how good it felt
to be held by you.
You wanna make a baby?
Yes.
Yeah.